Guide to the Henry Knox Sherrill Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Henry Knox Sherrill Family Papers
1859-2015
RG 67
Yale University Divinity School Library
29
(56 boxes)
These papers relate primarily to the life and work of Henry Knox Sherrill and his son Henry Williams Sherrill. The papers document Henry Knox Sherrill's career as an Episcopal rector, Bishop of Massachusetts, and Presiding Bishop of the Episcopal Church, his wartime chaplaincy work (in France during World War I and as Chairman of the United States General Commission on Chaplains during World War II), his ecumenical leadership as President of the National Council of Churches and the World Council of Churches, and his service to institutions such as Yale University and Massachusetts General Hospital. Henry Williams Sherrill was a graduate of Yale College, Union Theological Seminary and Virginia Theological Seminary. He was an Episcopal priest who served parishes in Michigan and Ohio and for many years was chairman of the Cheswick Center, a research and education trust for study and improvement in nonprofit governance.
Sherrill, Henry Knox, 1890-1980
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Sherrill family.
Biographical / Historical
1890 Nov 6 Born in Brooklyn, New York, son of Henry Williams and Maria (Prue) Knox Mills Sherrill
1906 Graduated from Polytechnic Preparatory School, Brooklyn
1906-1907 Year spent at Hotchkiss School, Lakeville, Connecticut
1911 Graduated from Yale College
1914 Graduated from Episcopal Theologlcal School, Cambridge, Massachusetts
1914 Jun 7 Ordained to the deaconate
1914-1917 Assistant minister, Trinity Church, Boston, Massachusetts
1917-1919 Red Cross chaplain of the Massachusetts General Hospital, Base Hospital Six; service in France (transferred from status of Red Cross chaplain to Army chaplain, First Lieutenant,1918)
1919-1923 Rector of Church of Our Saviour, Brookline, Massachusetts
1921 Married to Barbara Harris who became the mother of his children: Henry Williams, Edmund Knox, Franklin Goldthwaite, and Barbara Prue
1923 Received calls from St. James' Church, Chicago; St. Paul's Church, Rochester; Trinity Church, Boston
1923-1930 Rector of Trinity Church, Boston
1928 Elected Bishop Coadjutor of the Diocese of Pennsylvania. Declined position.
1928 Became trustee of Massachusetts General Hospital. Was Chairman of the Board 1934-1946.
1929 Granted honorary D.D. by Yale University. Numerous honorary degrees followed in the years to come.
1930 May 8 Elected Bishop of Massachusetts
1930 Oct 14 Consecration as Bishop of Massachusetts
1932 Sep Mother, Maria Knox Sherrill, died
1933 Mar Brother, Franklin Goldthwaite Sherrill, died
1934 Elected a "successor" fellow of the Yale Corporation
1941 Published William Lawrence, Later Years of a Happy Life
1943 Vice-chairman of United States General Commission on Chaplains, later Chairman. Traveled to Aleutian Islands in September, 1943 to visit chaplains and men on duty there.
1945 Apr Visited troops and chaplains in Europe on behalf of General Commission of Chaplains.
1945 Dec Visited Germany as part of Federal Council of Churches delegation
1946 Elected Presiding Bishop of Episcopal Church
1946 Appointed by President Truman to the Committee on Civil Rights
1947 Jan 14 Installed as Presiding Bishop
1948 Lyman Beecher lecturer at Yale Divinity School; lectures published as The Church's Ministry in Our Time.
1948 Attended Lambeth Conference in England
1949 General Convention of Episcopal Church in San Francisco
1949 Operation for intestinal ailment
1950-1952 President of newly formed National Council of Churches of Christ in the U.S.A.
1952 General Convention of Episcopal Church in Boston
1953 Visited Japan, Korea, Okinawa, Philippines
1954 Anglican Conference, Minneapolis
1954 Elected as one of the Presidents of the World Council of Churches at the Second General Assembly, Evanston thereby member of Executive and Central Committees. Served as WCC President until 1961.
1955 General Convention of Episcopal Church in Honolulu. HKS made decision to shift location from Houston due to problems of racial segregation.
1955 Visited Australia
1956 Visited U.S.S.R. as part of National Council of Churches delegation
1958 Appeared on "Person to Person" television show with Edward R. Murrow
1958 Attended Lambeth Conference in England
1958 General Convention of Episcopal Church in Miami Beach. HKS's successor elected. Son, Edmund, elected as Bishop of Central Brazil.
1958 Nov Retired as Presiding Bishop
1962 Published autobiography: Among Friends
1968 Operation for gall bladder
1980 May 11 Died
For more detailed information, see Sherrill's autobiography, Among Friends (Little, Brown and Company, Boston, 1962) and the obituaries and tributes contained in Series III, Box 36. List of Sherrill family members
Henry Knox Sherrill
Barbara Harris Sherrill (died May 6, 1986)
Henry Williams Sherrill (Harry, HWS) m. Patty, children: Rebecca (Becky), Barbara, and Henry Sinclair (Sinny)
Edmund Knox Sherrill (Neddo) m. Betty, children: Mary, Henry Knox Sherrill II, and Elisabeth (Bunny)
Franklin Goldthwaite Sherrill (FGS, Goldy) m. Mary, children: Ann, Sarah and Edmund Knox Sherrill II
Barbara Prue Sherrill (Prusie) m. Mason Wilson, Jr. children: Mason and Henry
Biographical / Historical
1922 Nov 14 Born in Boston, MA, son of Henry Knox Sherrill and Barbara Harris Sherrill
1941 Graduated from Milton Academy
1943-1946 Served in U.S. Army
1947 Graduated from Yale College, class of 1945
1947-1948 Attended Union Theological Seminary, NY
1950 Graduated from Virginia Theological Seminary, Alexandria, VA
1950 Ordained at St. Paul's Episcopal Cathedral, Boston
1952-1952 Parish ministry: Christ Church, Grosse Pointe, MI
1952-1965 Parish ministry: Church of the Redeemer, Cincinnati, OH
1964-1969 Executive Officer of Diocese of Southern Ohio
1969-2001 Served with various non-profit and charitable organizations, including co-founder of Consultation Search, co-founder (1971) and chairman (1971-1991) of the Cheswick Center. Among the Cheswick Center projects he was involved with were the innovative Board Mentor Program, in conjunction with the Association of Governing Boards and Universities, and the Program for the Public Service Management of Religious Institutions at the General Theological Seminary, Berkeley, Calif. He also consulted with the Menniger Foundation, Topeka, Kansas, the Department of Psychiatry of the University of Cincinnati Medical School in Cincinnati, Ohio, and the Clorox Company. He served as president of the Good Samaritan Foundation in Wilmington, DE and on the boards of the Corporation of the Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston; the Center of Effective Philanthropy, Cambridge, Mass.; the Children's Home, Cincinnati, Ohio; the Slingerland Institute, Seattle, Wash., and the Arizona branch of the International Dyslexia Society, among many others.
2001 Mar 21 Died in Peoria, AZ
Scope and Contents
The collection provides valuable documentation of Henry Knox Sherrill's career as an Episcopal rector, Bishop of Massachusetts, and Presiding Bishop of the Episcopal Church, as well as his involvement in wartime chaplaincy work, his ecumenical leadership as President of the National Council of Churches and World Council of Churches, and his service to institutions such as Yale University and Massachusetts General Hospital. Official correspondence and documents stemming from these various positions are not present to any great extent. The strength of the collection lies in its completeness of biographical documentation. It illuminates the decisions made by Sherrill along his career path, and provides insight into the personality that won to him so many friends and admirers over the years.
An addendum added in 2009 includes documentation of the life and work of Henry Williams Sherrill, son of Henry Knox and Barbara Sherrill. Henry Williams Sherrill was an Episcopal priest who served parishes in Michigan and Ohio and for many years was chairman of the Cheswick Center, a research and education trust for study and improvement in nonprofit governance.
Henry Knox Sherrill and his wife Barbara were conscientious in saving newspaper and magazine clippings, letters and programs describing his activities. These materials also serve to document issues and events in the Episcopal Church during the period of Sherrill's career. The numerous sermons, addresses, messages and articles which Sherrill delivered and wrote are also available in the collection. A large section of memorabilia includes artifacts presented to Sherrill as gifts and tributes, as well as the numerous honorary degrees and citations which were granted to Sherrill. In addition to providing insight into Sherrill's life and work, the collection provides useful information about the prominent Episcopal Church leaders who were Sherrill's friends and compatriots, such as Henry Hobson, Appleton Lawrence, William Lawrence, Alexander Mann, William Scarlett and Henry St. George Tucker. Extensive correspondence and clippings also document the close friendship which developed between the Sherrills and the Archbishop of Canterbury, Geoffrey Fisher, and his wife, Rosamond.
The first Series is divided into two sections, Family Correspondence and General Correspondence. The Family Correspondence includes numerous early letters of Henry Knox Sherrill to his mother and brother. Letters from his student days at Yale and at the Episcopal Theological School provide an interesting commentary on college and seminary life in the early 1900's. There is a substantial amount of correspondence from the Sherrill children. Also included in the Family Correspondence section are letters of family members which are not to or from Sherrill. There are three letters from the eighteenth century, written by ancestors of Sherrill. The correspondence of Barbara Harris Sherrill contains letters of interest from Rosamond Fisher, wife of the Archbishop of Canterbury, and from the wives of other Episcopal Church leaders. Letters of condolence received by Barbara Harris Sherrill after the death of Sherrill are also included in this section.
The General Correspondence is divided into three subsections:
1. Prominent correspondents
2. Chronological sequence of correspondence received at notable events in Sherrill's life
3. Miscellaneous correspondence
The vast majority of letters in this section were written to Henry Knox Sherrill. In his autobiography Sherrill wrote that when he first took office as Presiding Bishop, "The mail was voluminous, and I tried to answer every letter promptly and to sign each one myself."( Among Friends, p. 224.) It is certain that Sherrill wrote many letters throughout his career, but very few copies of his letters are available in this collection. The arrangement of the General Correspondence is based upon the filing system which had been established by Sherrill. Some of the "prominent" correspondents are so designated by virtue of their having had separate folders allocated to them in Sherrill's files.
No letters from the over 150 prominent correspondents in subsection 1 will be found in the chronological sequence of subsection 2 (excepting a bound volume of letters presented to Sherrill at his retirement), or among the miscellaneous correspondence of subsection 3. Religious leaders among Sherrill's prominent correspondents included George K. A. Bell, Charles Henry Brent, Samuel McCrea Cavert, Henry Sloane Coffin, Angus Dun, Geoffrey Fisher, Wilfred Grenfell, William Lawrence, G. Bromley Oxnam, James DeWolf Perry, William Temple, Henry St. George Tucker and Henry P. Van Dusen. Sherrill had small amounts of correspondence with political leaders such as Dean Acheson, Prescott Bush. Dwight D. Eisenhower, Eleanor Roosevelt, Leverett Saltonstall and Harry S. Truman. He also corresponded with individuals prominent in Yale affairs, such as James Rowland Angell, Kingman Brewster, A. Whitney Griswold, Wilmarth "Lefty" Lewis and Charles Seymour.
Correspondence surrounding fifteen notable events in Henry Knox Sherrill's life is located in subsection 2 of the General Correspondence. For each event the letters are arranged alphabetically by author or recipient other than Sherrill. There are letters of advice and encouragement sent in 1923 and 1928 when Sherrill was faced with major decisions about his career. There are congratulatory letters sent when Sherrill received his honorary D.D. from Yale in 1929, when he was elected Bishop of Massachusetts in 1930, on the occasions the fifteenth and twenty-fifth anniversaries of his consecration in 1945 and 1955, when he was elected Presiding Bishop in 1947, when retired in 1958, and on the occasion of his 80th birthday in 1970. Sherrill received numerous letters of sympathy following the deaths of his mother and brother in 1932 and 1933, and following his operation in 1949. Other batches of letters are related to Sherrill's publications, William Lawrence: Later Years of a Happy Life (1943) and Among Friends (1962), his 1945 trip to Europe for the General Commission on Army and Navy Chaplains, and his 1958 appearance on the "Person to Person" television program.
The small amount of miscellaneous correspondence in subsection 3 consists of letters not written by prominent individuals and not related to any of the fifteen events noted in subsection 2.
Series II, Sermons, Writings, contains nearly 300 sermons, addresses, prayers, messages, and articles written by Henry Knox Sherrill between 1914 and 1972,as well as reviews of his major publications, and the manuscript of his autobiography. The subject matter of the material in this Series varies from general statements on theology and Church doctrine, to biographical tributes, to commentary on specific occasions before specific organizations. There are a great many statements issued by Sherrill in his capacity as head of the Episcopal Church from 1947 to 1958. The titles of Sherrill's writings illustrate the wide range of his interests and involvements.
The Biographical Documentation of Series III includes newspaper and magazine clippings, programs, reports, news releases, and other items related to the activities of Henry Knox Sherrill from 1906 through 1980. Pocket size appointment books that detail daily activities are available for most of the years between 1928 and 1957. Material related to the various committees Sherrill served on is available, including the Yale Committee on the Relationship of the University and the New Haven Hospital (1944) and the President's Committee on Civil Rights (1947). Meetings of the Episcopal Church General Convention and House of Bishops, the National Council of Churches, World Council of Churches, and Lambeth Conference are documented, as well as trips taken by Sherrill and the occasions honoring him. Following the chronological sequence of material are one folder of undated material and eleven oversize scrapbooks dating from 1919 to 1965. Some of the scrapbooks document a single event while others are compendiums of material from a number of years.
Series IV, Subject File, contains material related to individuals, organizations and issues of interest to Henry Knox Sherrill. The material in this Series is primarily printed or typescript. Though it is less directly related to Sherrill's activities than the Biographical Documentation of Series III, it provides biographical information by defining the context in which he worked. Sherrill collected material related to family members and to colleagues such as Theodore Ferris, Geoffrey Fisher, Henry Hobson, and William Lawrence. The folder of material related to Phillips Brooks contains two letters written by Brooks, to "Arthur" in 1877 and to Charles L. Harrison in 1886. Organizations and institutions documented in the Subject File include the Episcopal Church Foundation, the Good Samaritan Inc., Massachusetts General Hospital, the National Council of Churches, Seabury House, Greenwich, and Trinity Church, Boston. Also included in this Series is a card file which will refer the researcher to correspondence and other material in the Sherrill Papers relating to various individuals and organizations. This file was compiled by Sherrill, his wife, and their secretaries, and has location indications which are no longer accurate in the present arrangement of the Sherrill Papers. The file is of interest, however, for its listing in one alphabetical sequence of topics which can now be located in the various Series described by this register.
The Personal Items and Memorabilia of Series V are divided into five sections:
A. Artifacts
B. Books
C. Phonograph records
D. Academic hoods
E. Citations, degrees, diplomas
Most of the artifacts were gifts presented to Henry Knox Sherrill in recognition of his service to various organizations. They are described briefly, with inscriptions and dates noted as available. The books of Section B were of particular personal significance to Sherrill because they were presented to him by friends or document events and organizations of interest to him. Other books which came with the Sherrill Papers have been added to the general collection of the Library. These books are listed on pages 69-73. Section C includes recordings of Sherrill addresses and Yale-related events. The majority of the twenty-three academic hoods in section D are identified according to the granting institutions, but a few are described only by color. In section E are Sherrill's earned and honorary diplomas, citations from organizations he served, and certificates documenting his appointment to various positions. One item in this section relates to Sherrill's wife, a certificate from the United States Navy in appreciation of her wartime hospital work.
The Photographs of Series Vl are divided into four sections:
A. Portraits of Henry Knox Sherrill
B. Portraits of family members
C. Chronological sequence
D. Oversize photographs and photograph albums
The majority of photographs in this Series are identified and dated. Photographs in the chronological sequence primarily document important events in Sherrill's career.
Series VII, Addendum - 2009, includes documentation of three generations of Sherrills: Henry Williams Sherrill (1853-1899 - father of Henry Knox Sherrill), Henry Knox Sherrill (1896-1979), and Henry Williams Sherrill (1922-2001 - son of Henry Knox Sherrill). The series includes family correspondence, general correspondence, writings, sermons, notes, and photographs. A detailed inventory of documents and photographs is available in the first folder of the series.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1776-1986
II. Sermons, Writings, 1914-1972, n.d.
III. Biographical Documentation, 1900-1986
IV. Subject File, 1832-1978.
V. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1885-1968, n.d.
VI. Photographs, 1891-1978, n.d..
VII. Addendum: 2009, 1859-2003, n.d.
Ecumenical movement; United States -- Religion; Bishops; Clergy; Ecumenists; Bell, G. K. A. (George Kennedy Allen), 1883-1958; Brent, Charles Henry, 1862-1929; Cavert, Samuel McCrea, 1888-1976; Coffin, Henry Sloane, 1877-1954; Fisher of Lambeth, Geoffrey Francis Fisher, Baron, 1887-1972; Grenfell, Wilfred Thomason, Sir, 1865-1940; Sherrill, Henry Knox, 1890-1980; Van Dusen, Henry P. (Henry Pitney), 1897-1975; Episcopal Church; National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America; World Council of Churches; Lambeth Conference
- Correspondence, 1776-1986; Series I
  - Family Correspondence
    - 1. HKS correspondence with family members
      - HKS to/from mother and brother, 1901-1927 (Box 1, Folder 1-17)
      - HKS to/from mother and brother, 1933, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - HKS to/from Barbara Harris Sherrill, 1925-1956, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 19, 20)
      - HKS to son Harry, 1948-1962,n.d. (Box 37, Folder 688)
      - HKS to son Neddo, 1945 (Box 37, Folder 688)
      - HKS to children, 1934-1962,n.d. (Box 37, Folder 689)
      - HKS and BHS from Barbara Prue Sherrill, 1948 -1977, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 690-692)
      - HKS and BHS from Edmund Knox Sherrill, 1943-1984, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 693-700)
      - HKS and BHS from Franklin Goldthwaite Sherrill, 1948-1968, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 701-705)
      - HKS and BHS from Henry Williams Sherrill, 1930-1985, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 706-707)
      - HKS and BHS from Betty (Mrs. Edmund Knox Sherrill), 1953-1983, n.d. (Box 38, Folder 708-714)
      - HKS and BHS from Mary (Mrs. Franklin Goldthwaite Sherrill), 1953-1977,n.d. (Box 39, Folder 715-716)
      - HKS and BHS from Mason Wilson, Jr. (husband of Prue), 1983 (Box 39, Folder 717)
      - HKS and BHS from Patty (Mrs. Henry Williams Sherrill), 1948,1953,n.d. (Box 39, Folder 718)
      - HKS and BHS from granddaughter, Ann, 1981,n.d. (Box 39, Folder 719)
      - HKS and BHS from grandson, Edmund Knox Sherrill II, 1981-1982 (Box 39, Folder 720)
      - HKS and BHS from granddaughter, Elisabeth Sherrill deLemos (Bunny), 1981,1985,n.d. (Box 39, Folder 721)
      - HKS and BHS from grandson, Edmund Knox Sherrill II, 1982-1983 (Box 39, Folder 722)
      - HKS and BHS from grandson, Henry Sinclair Sherrill, 1982,n.d. (Box 39, Folder 723)
      - HKS and BHS from grandsons, Henry and Mason Wilson, 1976-1977 (Box 39, Folder 724)
      - HKS and BHS from granddaughter, Mary, 1977-1985,n.d. (Box 39, Folder 725)
      - HKS and BHS from granddaughter, Rebecca, 1974,1977,n.d. (Box 39, Folder 726)
      - BHS from granddaughter, Sarah (Box 39, Folder 727)
      - HKS and BHS from grandchildren and their spouses, 1964-1980,n.d (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - HKS and BHS from her parents, 1927,1946,1948 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 2. Correspondence of family members other than HKS
      - Henry Sherrill, 1776, 1782 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - ___ Knox, 1798 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Henry Williams Sherrill, 1890, 1898, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Maria Knox Sherrill, 1901, 1921, 1922, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Franklin Goldthwaite Sherrill, 1903-1909 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Barbara Harris Sherrill with Rosamond, Lady Fisher, 1948-1985, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28-32)
      - Barbara Harris Sherrill with Frances Temple, 1946-1974 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Barbara Harris Sherrill -- Miscellaneous: Adams - Byrd (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Barbara Harris Sherrill -- Miscellaneous: Carpenter - Dykman (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Barbara Harris Sherrill -- Miscellaneous: Edgar - Gulick (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Barbara Harris Sherrill -- Miscellaneous: Hale - Judge (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Barbara Harris Sherrill -- Miscellaneous: Kennedy - Lyte (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Barbara Harris Sherrill -- Miscellaneous: McCain - Morrison (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Barbara Harris Sherrill -- Miscellaneous: Nash - Quin (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Barbara Harris Sherrill -- Miscellaneous: Ramsey - Sibley (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Barbara Harris Sherrill -- Miscellaneous: Slattery - Sykes (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Barbara Harris Sherrill -- Miscellaneous: Taylor - Yule (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Barbara Harris Sherrill -- Miscellaneous: First names and unidentified (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - BHS -- Letters received after death of HKS: Adams - Blake (Box 35, Folder 660)
      - BHS -- Letters received after death of HKS: Bowen - Carpenter (Box 35, Folder 661)
      - BHS -- Letters received after death of HKS: Caswell - Curtis (Box 35, Folder 662)
      - BHS -- Letters received after death of HKS: Eckerson - Gesner (Box 35, Folder 663)
      - BHS -- Letters received after death of HKS: Giamatti - Howard (Box 35, Folder 664)
      - BHS -- Letters received after death of HKS: Hunt - Krumm (Box 35, Folder 665)
      - BHS -- Letters received after death of HKS: Lamb - Maxwell (Box 35, Folder 666)
      - BHS -- Letters received after death of HKS: Meader - Nyberg (Box 35, Folder 667)